

# George**Alestas**

Physicist - PhD Candidate (1)

#### **Affiliation** University of Ioannina

# **Professional Summary**

# Website

A highly motivated researcher specializing in Cosmology and Astrophysics. I am proficient in the theoretical and numerical exploration of cosmological models, including cosmological parameter inference using various well-known MCMC software. I have worked on several **georgealestas.github.io** aspects of the Hubble and  $S_8$  tensions. Fast learner and excellent collaborator.

#### Tel & Skype (+30) 6989964269 alestasg

# **Education**

#### 2018 - 2022 PhD Candidate

University of Ioannina

Ph.D Thesis: "ACDM and the Implications of the Hubble Tension" Supervisor: Prof. Leandros Perivolaropoulos

# Mail

g.alestas@uoi.gr alestasg@gmail.com

#### 2015 - 2017 Master's Degree in Theoretical and Mathematical Physics, **Astronomy and Astrophysics**

University of Patras

Upper First Class Honours, G.P.O was 8.87.

M.Sc Thesis: "Thermodynamic Properties of Self-Gravitating Systems",

grade: 10/10

Thesis Advisor: Asst. Prof. Charis Anastopoulos

#### Languages Greek → Native **English** → Fluent

#### 2010 - 2014 **Bachelor's Degree in Physics**

University of Patras

Upper Second Class Honours, top 4 percent of my class. My specialization was Theoretical and Mathematical Physics, Astronomy and Astrophysics. Specialization courses G.P.O was 8,36.

B.Sc Thesis: "Cosmological Perturbation Theory and Gravitational Waves", grade: 10/10, Indicative Courses and grades:

- 1. Astrophysics I: 8/10
- 2. Astrophysics II: 8.5/10
- 3. Computational Physics: 9.5/10
- 4. Elementary Particles and Cosmology: 8/10

# **Publication Record**

Eight papers (highlighted most important) with a total of more than 160 citations and h-index = 7. The codes used in the analysis of all the papers are publicly available at my GitHub page. Click here for my up to date InspireHEP profile.

- 1. Constraining a late time transition of  $G_{\text{eff}}$  using low-z galaxy survey data, G. Alestas, L. Perivolaropoulos and K. Tanidis, arXiv: 2201.05846 (Under peer-review)
- 2. Late-transition vs smooth H(z) deformation models for the resolution of the Hubble crisis, G. Alestas, D. Camarena, E. Di Valentino, L. Kazantzidis, V. Marra, S. Nesseris and L. Perivolaropoulos, arXiv: 2110.04336 (Under peer-review)
- 3. Hints for a gravitational constant transition in Tully-Fisher data, G. Alestas, I. Antoniou and L. Perivolaropoulos, Universe 7 (2021) 366, DOI: 10.3390/universe7100366, (More than 10 citations)
- 4. Late time approaches to the Hubble tension deforming H(z), worsen the growth tension, G. Alestas, L. Perivolaropoulos, Mon.Not.Roy.Astron.Soc. 504 (2021) 3, 3956-3962, DOI: 10.1093/mnras/stab1070, (More than 20 citations)

- 5. A w-M phantom transition at zt<0.1 as a resolution of the Hubble tension, G. Alestas, L. Kazantzidis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 103 (2021) 8, 083517, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.103.083517, (More than 25 citations)
- 6. Existence and Stability of Static Spherical Fluid Shells in a Schwarzschild-Rindler-anti-de Sitter Metric, G. Alestas, G.V. Kraniotis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 102 (2020) 104015, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.102.104015, (More than 5 citations)
- 7.  $H_0$  tension, phantom dark energy, and cosmological parameter degeneracies, G. Alestas, L. Kazantzidis, L. Perivolaropoulos, Phys.Rev.D 101 (2020) 12, 123516, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.101.123516, (More than 70 citations)
- 8. Evading Derrick's theorem in curved space: Static metastable spherical domain wall, Alestas G., Perivolaropoulos L., Phys.Rev.D 99 (2019) no.6, 064026, DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevD.99.064026, (More than 5 citations)

# **Scholarships & Grants**

- Fellow of the Greek State and the European Union (European Social Fund ESF) through the Operational Programme "Competitiveness, Entrepreneurship and Innovation 2014-2020 (EPAnEK)"
- Fellow of the Greek State and the European Union (European Social Fund ESF) through the Operational Programme "Human Resources Development, Education and Lifelong Learning 2014-2020"
- European Cooperation in Science & Technology (COST) grant for a short term scientific mission (STSM) in the context of the action "CA15117 Cosmology and Astrophysics Network for Theoretical Advances and Training Actions (CANTATA)" and the project "Search for Hints of Modified Gravity in Cosmological Data"

# Conferences Attended & Talks Given

- HEP 2020 38th Conference on Recent Developments in High Energy Physics and Cosmology, September 2021, Athens, Greece.
- 16th Marcel Grossmann Meeting MG16, July 2021, Rome, Italy, (Talk)
- 19th online Conference in the String Phenomenology Conference Series, June 2020, Boston, United States.
- 9th Korea Institute of Advanced Study (KIAS) Workshop on Cosmology and Structure Formation webinar, November 2020, Seoul, South Korea
- Workshop on Quantum Fields and Nonlinear Phenomena, SEENET-MTP-CERN-ICTP Joint Meeting, 2020, Romania, (Talk)
- SEENET-MTP Balkan School on High Energy and Particle Physics: Theory and Phenomenology, 2019, loannina, (Talk)
- HEP 2019 Recent Developments on High Energy Physics and Cosmology, 2019, Athens

#### **Research Interests**

Theoretical Cosmology, Observational Cosmology, Hubble Tension, Modified Gravity Theories, Dark Energy, Data Analysis, Gravitational waves, Soliton Physics.

# **Programming Knowledge**

- · Linux, Windows
- Python, C/C++, Fortran, HTML
- COSMOMC/CAMB, MontePython/Class, Mathematica, Matlab

#### Skills

Cosmology, Theoretical Astrophysics, Computational Physics, General Relativity, Data Analysis

# **Referee Work**

I am a referee for the Monthly Notices of the Royal Astronomical Society (MNRAS) journal. For more details please click **here** to visit my Publons profile.

# **Teaching Experience**

#### 2021-22 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Classical Electrodynamics I (5th Semester Core Course - 52), my duties were:

- 1. The tutoring of third year students.
- 2. The grading of weekly assignments.

#### 2021-22 Teaching Assistant

University of Ioannina

Gravity and General Theory of Relativity (Advanced Undergraduate Elective Course – 106), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2020-21 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Cosmology (Advanced Undergraduate Elective Course - 105), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2020-21 **Teaching Assistant**

University of loannina

Gravity and General Theory of Relativity (Advanced Undergraduate Elective Course – 106), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2019-20 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Ioannina

Classical Electrodynamics I (5th Semester Core Course - 52), my duties were:

1. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

2016-17 **Teaching Assistant** 

University of Patras

Astrophysics Laboratory (TAE450), my duties were:

- 1. The tutoring of third and fourth year students.
- 2. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.

#### 2016-17 **Teaching Assistant**

University of Patras

Astronomy Laboratory (TAE451), my duties were:

- 1. The tutoring of third and fourth year students.
- 2. The grading of weekly assignments and reports.
- 3. Demonstrating the use of Astronomical equipment.

# **Societies**

- Student Member of the American Physical Society (APS)
- Junior Member of the Hellenic Society on Relativity, Gravitation and Cosmology

# **Professional References**

Prof. Leandros Perivolaropoulos - leandros@uoi.gr (PhD Advisor)

Asst. Prof. Savvas Nesseris - savvas.nesseris@csic.es

Dr. Eleonora Di Valentino - E.Divalentino@shef.ac.uk

Asst. Prof. Panagiota E. Christopoulou - pechris@physics.upatras.gr